sorry was it supposed to be $30 million
per like the athletes are supposed to
make $30 million a piece off these
fights when we say that there's
controversy this is this is part of it
so we have this young gun this exciting
Bulgarian lifter versus one of the
greatest Chinese weightlifters in
history it was like on the on the
trajectory of like oh she's going to be
the fittest woman on Earth this year it
I was going to say it was one of the
more shocking and surprising midseason
announcements to ever
happen hey folks welcome to strength
weekly which keeps you up to date on
everything you need to know from around
the barbell game and if you're a
strongman fan the stones game because
you know they don't just lift barbells
anyway I'm David thas toow joined by the
incomparable Phillip Bartholomew
Blackman that's not his middle name but
I always forget it and we have an action
packed strength weekly for you this week
action-packed including some controversy
Phil strength Sports and controversy
they go together like protein and
creatine am I right back me up here uh
yeah we might as well just say we're
talking about controversy this week not
strength Sports it's just controversy
welcome to controversy weekly brought to
you by strength weekly a subset of
barbend media okay Phil we have four hot
off the presses stories this week first
and foremost Brian Shaw's highly
anticipated mixed martial arts debut
gets postponed Carlos Nasser of Bulgaria
sets a junior world record snatch of 176
kg at the European weightlifting
championships on home soil Hometown hero
Mal O'Brien who finished second place at
the CrossFit Games two years ago and sat
out the 2023 season has announced she's
also sitting out the 2024 season it
significantly impacts the women's field
at this year's CrossFit Games and the
2025 Sheffield powerlifting Championship
has been scheduled for January 2025 we
talk about that and I argue with Phil
because I've been doing some thinking
and I disagree with Phil on a lot and
it's kept me up at night but here we are
recording I'm going to get it all out on
camera it sure is cheaper than therapy
fill of all these stories which get you
most amped today oh I I was anticipating
in 2024 that I want I wanted to see the
clash between Mal O Brien and Emma
Lawson and tia Clair Tumi or and Laura
Horath you know battling for the podium
and now that Mal o brien's not going to
be in the 2024 season I mean that was
the the biggest news to me this week so
I'm excited to get into that well we
have a change battle there with uh one
fewer player in the field let's segue
that right into actual battle hand toand
combat
Shaw was supposed to battle Martin Fjord
and that fight was already supposed to
have happened it was supposed to have
happened on Fe February 17th it didn't
happen so the fight has been postponed
maybe cancelled and I want to be very
clear here everything we know is from
what Brian Shaw has said and from what
Mitchell Hooper has posted we don't
necessarily know the details Brian Shaw
referenced a breach of contract several
times we don't know what that breach of
contract was so everything we're about
to say is coming coming from three main
things what Brian Shaw has said publicly
what Mitchell Hooper has said publicly
and the fact that none of these guys
ended up fighting in Qatar like they
were scheduled to do on February 17th so
let's keep that in mind and let's move
into what the heck is going on yeah
tagging also on to the fact that Brian
Shaw wasn't making his MMA debut neither
were the other two Elite strong men on
the card reigning World's Strongest Man
Mitchell Hooper was supposed to take on
Eddie Hall in their MMA debuts and that
fight didn't happen either now what we
learned from Brian Shaw on their end was
that there was a breach of contract
where there was a large amount of money
promised to these athletes now the
numbers that we heard uh from Mitchell
Hooper on his Instagram story was that
it was a $30 million contract down to A3
million contract now that is still a lot
of money but there was a Fallout of
contract the event still actually
happened the the fight event that was
scheduled still took place it just
didn't happen with any of the strong men
actually competing in any of those
fights that we were initially built up
for so what we got was that it's
postponed but it sounds like it's just
straight canell from the feedback that
was given from the athletes after this
supposed breach of contract sorry was it
supposed to be $30 million per like the
athletes were supposed to make $30
million a piece off these fights when we
say that there's controversy this is
this is part of it like this was the
first glimpse into how much money was
actually being posed to these athletes
who had never stepped into the ring
before so 30 million per sounds
outrageously
however who knows maybe that like that
that is I guess something that could
happen even down to 3 million I mean you
that's a significant cut but 3 million
for athletes that have never stepped
into the ring or into the Octagon before
is still a very large prize purse but
yeah I mean if you were if you were
preparing to make that kind of money and
then have it come down you know a couple
weeks before the fight actually is
supposed to happen I I I would be upset
too and Brian Shaw like did did relay
that he was very frustrated and
disappointed that the fight was being
postponed Brian Shaw has said publicly
that he was doing this not so much for
the love of the fight game but to secure
his family's financial future yeah I
mean if if we don't know like we we
haven't seen these contracts so we don't
know but if the contracts were like up
to $30 million a piece yeah I'd say
that's a step in securing one's
financial future and one's family's
financial future it's a weird situation
it's a very weird situation I know we
were really excited also Mitchell Hooper
reigning World's Strongest Man was set
to compete at the Arnold strongman
classic just weeks at basically two
weeks after it was sort of this like
what is going on here the incentives
must be huge and Mitchell's post gives
some insight to the fact that the
incentives were huge they were in these
seven figures maybe even into well into
the mid eight figures when it comes to
like what these athletes could have made
I'm not saying we won't see these
athletes in in the Octagon because I
think there's interest we see that if
the if the money is right there's
there's interest in these athletes
fighting the whole thing is confusing
right now I wonder if more information
will come out the event did happen it
just didn't feature Martin Fjord
Mitchell Hooper Eddie Hall or Brian Shaw
right it just happened without those
folks on the card and it's also
interesting to see because all four of
these guys have been training they've
been training in MMA right and Brian
Shaw has been very public about how hard
he's been training how much he's been
dedicated to this style of training I
wonder if the there's an added in setad
of now because the these athletes have
explored training in this discipline in
this fighting style maybe they want to
utilize that maybe they want to monetize
that yeah uh Hooper had shared that he
was sort of concerned with how the
transparency of the event was going down
from the jump and that he didn't train
as hard as it may have been led to
believe at the beginning when it was
first announced though Shaw was
consistently training in the gym and
giving updates routinely on how he was
training so the way that they went about
it was different but Hooper seemed to
have like sniffed that there was
something aai early on and and then it
just so happened that there there was so
he didn't train as hard I mean granted
he had something else to train for and
where that Shaw didn't I mean Hooper is
the reigning Arnold Classic champion and
he will attempt to defend in Columbus so
this will not be the last we hear of it
I I expect that there will be a
rehashing and I imagine the athletes too
will come back to the table because
where the money is is where the athletes
will go all right Phil well one event
that did go down and one athlete that
did perform is the European
weightlifting championships and Carlos
Nasser of bulgar still a junior
weightlifter and maybe a favorite maybe
a favorite or certainly a Podium
Contender heading into the Paris
Olympics well he done set a junior world
record snatch and guess what it was on
home soil because the competition was in
Bulgaria Phil what did Nasser do so
every time this guy steps onto the
platform I feel like we're talking about
world record implications in this case
he snatched a 176 kg or 388b record
snatch in the men's 89 kogam class now
this was at the 2024 European
weightlifting championships which as you
said took place in Sophia Bulgaria on
February 12th to the 20th so as we're
recording this the competition is still
wrapping up but NASA's part of it is
done and he has a record in the books
this is a big deal for NASA for a few
reasons one this is one of the last
qualifying events for the Paris Olympics
for weightlifting at the international
level snatch 176 he clean and jerk 215
ended with a 391 kgam total that's
actually 4 kilos below his best ever
total which is 395 nasar sits in second
place in the overall world rankings
behind Lee dyen of China with that 395
total it's interesting because China's
had these weight classes these men's
middle weight classes on lock for a
while NASA is coming out and saying that
he might really be able to battle for
gold in Paris against Lee daen of China
which was Unthinkable two years ago it
was
Unthinkable that a non-chinese athlete
would really have a shot this sets up
for me the 89 kilo class in Paris for
the men to be the most exciting men's
competition because we get to see NASA
who is dramatic on the platform and is
not afraid to take big jumps and not
afraid to go for World Records right
against Lee daen of China who is the
current number one ranked athlete in
that weight category so we have this
young gun this exciting Bulgarian lifter
versus one of the greatest Chinese
weight lifters in history I think it's
going to be an epic Throwdown in Paris
so I cannot think of a better potential
head-to-head a cross the body weight
categories for men or women in in Paris
yeah this category jumps out to me in
particular because in the previous
Olympic cycle when Lua xun of China was
also still in competing in 89 kilograms
China had to debate whether or not they
were going to send their like Flagship
gold medalist in Lou or if they were
going to send their like top ranked
lifter in Lee Dian and we've covered Lee
in in ways where it's like this dude
can't make weight because he's got too
much muscle on his frame like to see
NASA posting weights that are in range
of competing with Lee Dian I mean this
is it like Nasser is showing he is
capable that he is going to contend for
the top of the podium yeah I I think
that for NASA to be a high-profile
weightlifter from Bulgaria it is it is
there's a lot of national pride wrapped
up in Bulgarian weightlifting and to see
an athlete of his caliber compete uh at
this level has got to be exciting for
longtime Bulgarian weightlifting fans so
Carlos Nasser I'm going to throw it out
there most exciting athlete right most
exciting weightlifter on the planet
right now boom yeah g g given that he's
recovering from the insane injury that
he had before to come back so fast like
I mean what a story right if he actually
does some like magically win gold in
Paris what a trajectory he has had as
such a young athlete yeah and I mean uh
no signs of slowing down in fact quite
the opposite but let's talk about an
athlete who is taking a young athlete
who is taking a step back from
competition or at least continuing a
step back from competition and that's
Mal O'Brien of the United States she
finished in second place at the 2022
CrossFit Games at the time she was the
youngest ever Podium finisher at the
CrossFit games now that title has since
been usurped because Emma Lawson of
Canada uh was younger when she finished
on the podium last year in 20123 Mal
O'Brien was kind of considered the next
great thing finished second only to T
Clair Tumi in 2022 in 2023 partway
through the season decides to say she's
not going to compete uh took time off
for some unspecified personal reasons
some we've seen athletes do before
something we've seen young athletes do
before in recent strength weekly
broadcast have talked about how excited
we were for the women's field because
Tia's back defending CrossFit Games
Champion Lara Horvath is compeed you
have Emma Lawson of Canada right who has
her sit set on a title and then we said
hey M O'Brien's coming back Haley Adams
another young athlete um who's done
quite well at the games and has a string
of top 10 finishes is back this year but
O'Brien in a recent post shortly after
we recorded last week's strength week
weekly said she is taking this season
off uh she has moved to Hawaii just says
she is not necessarily done competing in
CrossFit but is going to be involved in
the sport in the community in other ways
Phil uh what did O'Brien say and what
reasons if any did she give she said and
I quote my focus overall is my
well-being as a person it's not
something I focused on almost ever I
won't be competing in the 2024 CrossFit
season it's not what I need in my life
right now she also said just because I'm
not competing in the 2024 season doesn't
mean that I won't ever I'm not putting a
timeline on anything I'll forever be a
part of the sport so we know that she
won't be competing in 2024 but 2025 is
still maybe maybe in play Maybe It's
2026 who knows but whenever she does she
said that she is still training it is
part of her life whether she's training
at the level she would need to to
compete at the highest levels unknown
but when she does come back I would
still consider her to be one of the top
players because in last season before
she decided to step down she was
competing with hwpo with Matt Frasier
you know and he's got a string of pretty
good finishes also she was doing very
very well before she's decided to
withdraw she won the worldwide open for
on the women's side and then she also
won the quarterfinals so it was like on
the on the trajectory of like oh she's
gonna be the fittest woman on Earth this
year I was gonna say it was one of the
more shocking and surprising
midseason announcements to ever happened
in the sport of Crossfit because she won
the open she won the quarterfinals and
then she withdrew and Phil by the way
you read those quotes so well you can
read quotes to me all day we pop those
on screen I'm like in it you know your
melodic tones professional voice actor
Phil Blackman fun fact anyway I do want
to point out Mala Brien is Young we do
not know all of her goals in life people
are multifaceted even people in CrossFit
are
multifaceted right as multifaceted as
the sport itself there's a lot of
pressure on these young athletes and
training is very much a full-time job
and then some it is is arduous it is
tough um I think when Matt Fraser
retired he talked a lot about how it's
you're giving not just 100% you're
trying to find more capacity you are
trying to find more to give to the sport
because it is that all consuming the
training the recovery everything it
seems like Mal O'Brien is to me is not
running away from anything but she's
running towards some life experiences
and a lifestyle that gives her a little
bit more happiness is what it seems like
for my completely unal ified perspective
and if that's the case I could not be
happier for this very young very
talented athlete to run toward something
and to run toward the things that give
her Joy right and it's okay to not get a
lot of joy and to not find your ultimate
joy in training for 12 hours a day and
recovering for the other 12 hours like
that's okay right that's even if you're
good at something it doesn't mean you
have to do it when Frasier has talked
about these young athletes before and
particularly Mal o Brian you know when
he was dominant in the sport he was not
a teenager the way that these athletes
are He has expressed that like somebody
like ma where they are in their training
versus where he was when he was at the
Pinnacle of the sport he was like they
are so far ahead of where I was you know
like granted Fraser was an Olympic
weightlifter you know he had broken his
back and had to recover from that when
he was younger but like his he was
surprised at how how early these
athletes were in their careers at the
level that they were already at but like
at the the cost of that is okay well
then you didn't live your your college
Years out you know you were in the gym
and we know from Fraser's training he
would wake up train eat sleep repeat
that was his life while he was the champ
and that you know like could he have
gone longer yeah but like when your life
is entirely consumed by like how can I
improve my sleep how can I improve my
diet like it is a full-time job that is
your entire life it's not like you can
step away and still be at the top of the
game you don't you don't clock out at
five right because if you're not
training you're recovering and you're
trying to optimize your recovery right
it it's it's so all that to say I am I'm
excited to see Haley Adams back this
season we won't see M O'Brien back this
season um but I I gotta respect M
O'Brien's approach here I think that
there's a lot more support she's getting
from the community than she would have
years ago because I think the community
has gotten a lot better at understanding
athletes as holist as people from more
holistic sense let's move on to our
final story of the day it's an
announcement the Sheffield powerlifting
championships one of the more exciting
events in powerlifting is returning in
2025 we just finished the 2024 version
it's coming back in January so a little
bit earlier January
2025 in Great Britain Jolly Old England
as I like to joke Phil do you think the
Sheffield powerlifting championships are
the most exciting thing in powerlifting
given what we saw at the 2024 Sheffield
which is only the second edition of the
contest oh yeah oh yeah it had some of
the best athletes in the world that all
qualified by competing at the world
championships in that same year and
hitting 95% of the world record total in
their weight class they came in 24
athletes 14 of them broke total World
Records I mean we saw on the women's
side 11 of them broke the world total
World Records we mentioned last week how
crazy it was that Amanda Lawrence she
broke the world record total in the
women's 84 kilogram class and came in a
11th like it still boggles the mine even
now so the fact that this competition is
coming back and is already announced uh
that there will be on January 26 2025
returning to Sheffield City Hall I mean
if it it's the it's the Super Bowl of
powerlifting at this point isn't it all
right I disagree I
disagree I think you're wrong I think
you're here's why here's why talk to how
how could it with these numbers David
how could it not be but I have a path
for it to become the premier event okay
okay I'm not just raising problems I'm
providing Solutions here all right
here's the deal I think that the
Sheffield is a great format and I think
it's exciting but I don't think it's the
most important or most exciting
competition in powerlifting because you
know what it doesn't have attached to it
you can't call yourself a world champion
you win the Sheffield you can't call
yourself a world champion you're the
Sheffield Champion cool I've never heard
of powerlifting oh you're into
powerlifting cool tell me about that
well I'm the Sheffield Champion what the
hell does that mean okay it's not a
world championship it's not a world
title and it doesn't carry that gravitas
I'm sorry but ultimately to take
something mainstream and to make it
relevant outside of these Niche strength
communities that we're in you gotta have
the world you got you gotta be champion
of the world right you gotta you got to
be able to say that right Arnold
strongman classic Champions great right
but I'm gonna be honest it ain't World's
Strongest Man it isn't that title and
you could you could whack you could are
you all you want about the quality of
competition but until the Sheffield
is considered a World Championship and
until it is designated as
such I do not think it has the same
relevancy especially crossover into the
mainstream as something like a a true
World
Championship what who would need to
designate it as such because from from
where I'm sitting the athletes pretty
the athletes designated it pretty well I
mean uh sio crushing 109% of the world
record total in the 69 kilogram women's
class just you know obliterating every
record that we've ever seen that weight
class I mean if anybody's going to
designate it I imagine it's the athletes
that are stepping on the podium and
actually putting in the work now I can
see what you're saying of like it
doesn't have the Optics of a world
championship but is that just because
the competition's still in its infancy I
think okay what what what is the
governing body that these athletes
compete at Phil for for the chef this is
the ipf this is the ipf right so I think
what the ipf could do to and again I
don't know if the ipf has the incentive
to do this but I think what would take
the Sheffield over the top is if the ipf
gave a designation and worked with the
Sheffield event organizers and said okay
okay we're going to bestow a special
title whoever wins The Sheffield it
could be on the men's side and the
women's side or just overall it could be
just overall Whatever Gets to call
themselves for one
year world's best
powerlifter I think that in order for
this competition to level up and to
become what it really could be the
winner or winners on the men's side and
the women's side has to be able to say
are the best powerlifter in the world in
a way that no one else can officially
say so yeah okay so you're saying you
you got to have a title so you yeah you
want them to walk out with a world
championship belt and be able to cut the
promo I I hear that so we started at
odds and now we're on the same page
because I agree that the competition is
where is is already at the level and it
should have the backing and title and
Optics to go along with it to really you
know because in in my view it's like
this is the All-Star Game you know this
is the the top of the top even though
there are some of the world's best that
aren't here right like that's the
exclusivity part of it which I feel like
is an additional you know level up
tacked onto it and why it's such a big
deal now so yeah I I agree I ipf let's
codify some stuff you could even call it
world's strongest powerlifter strongest
powerlifter in the world I'm not a
trademark lawyer these are just ideas
Phil I'm glad I like arguing with you
because I learn cuz you changed my mind
more often than not but I think I might
have brought you toward my game you
brought me around you brought me around
this time well the thing is you you
brought me around uh in in my
stubbornness you didn't change what I
wanted you gave me more of what I wanted
we're additive here we have a we have a
surplus mind we have a surplus mindset
we got a surplus mindset well until next
week when we'll bring a new surplus
mindset add more weight to the
proverbial mental bar I'm David Thomas
to joined by I'm Phil bman everybody
thank you so much for joining strength
weekly we will catch you next time